Finding Aid for Michigan Council Hostelling International records, 1941-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Council Hostelling International records 1941-2005
American Youth Hostels, inc. Michigan Council.
0745 Br 2
The Michigan Council Hostelling International records (1941-2005) consist of materials related to the Michigan Council and Metro Detroit Councils of Hostelling International-American Youth Hostels (HI-USA), formed in 1943. Records include administrative files, national and statewide boards and committee minutes, publications, topical files, photographs, slides, and scrapbooks documenting hostel trends, events, and programming for the latter half of the 20th century.
5 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor no. 2057 ) was received from the creator in February 2007.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Council of Hostelling International (HI), chartered in 1943, is a non-profit council that serves members and budget travelers across the entire state of Michigan. Its mission is to help people of all ages gain a greater understanding of the world, locally and internationally, through educational programs, cultural connections, recreational activities and positive hostelling experiences. The Michigan Council provides programming through workshops and unique trips, as well as social activities for members and the public including weekly hikes, monthly outings to ethnic restaurants, and special events.
The Michigan Council -- Hostelling International is part of the national organization, Hostelling International-American Youth Hostels (HI-USA), founded in 1934. HI-USA belongs to International Youth Hostel Federation (IYHF), a global network of 4,000 hostels in 60 countries.
The American Youth Hostel (AYH) organization began in 1934 and opened an office in Detroit in 1936 under the name Southeastern Michigan District of AYH. Detroit was not chartered by AYH until 1943 but began building hostels and programs under the first paid executive director, Miriam Hall. By the spring of 1938, there were 15 hostels open in Michigan. In 1939, AHY officially divided the United States into 8 regions that included subdivisions and districts. Detroit became the organization headquarters and equipment center.
The Michigan Council Hostelling International records (1941-2005) consist of administrative files, national and statewide boards and committee minutes, publications, topical files, photographs, slides, and scrapbooks documenting hostel trends, events, and programming for the latter half of the 20th century. The records have been organized into seven series of materials related to the Michigan Councils of HI-USA: Administration Files, Boards and Committees, Publications, Topical Files, Photographs, Slides, and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
American Youth Hostels, inc. Michigan Council.; Youth hostels--Michigan.; Tourist camps, hostels, etc.--Michigan.; Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore (Mich.); American Youth Hostels, inc. Metropolitan Detroit Council.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
American Youth Hostels, inc. Michigan Council.; Youth hostels--Michigan.; Tourist camps, hostels, etc.--Michigan.; American Youth Hostels, inc. Metropolitan Detroit Council.; Canoes--Michigan.; Cycling--Michigan.; Camping--Michigan.; Skiing--Michigan.; Ice skating--Michigan.; Sailboats--Michigan.; Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photograph albums.; Scrapbooks.; Slides.; Photographs.
- Administration
  Administration Files (0.5 linear feet) contain general administrative files, including budget and correspondence, as well as general information on hostelling, registration books, and strategic planning files.
  - Budget 1997, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Charter and Licensing Process (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General (Box 1)
    - Inspections (Box 1)
    - National Park Service (Box 1)
    - Updates from National CEO 2001-2004, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Founding Certificate 1943 (copy) (Box 1)
  - General Hostelling Information (Box 1)
  - Registration Books
    - 1944-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Strategic Planning
    - "Next Ten Years," 1996 (Box 1)
    - Strategic Plan 2001-2003 (Box 1)
    - Strategic Vision 1986-2006 (Box 1)
- Boards and Committees
  Boards and Committees (2.5 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically and contain records for the Board of Directors, Development Committee, Metro Detroit Council, and the National Board of Directors. Materials include mostly agendas and minutes, as well as correspondence, notes, annual reports, and national directories.
  - Board of Directors 1958-2005
    - Minutes
      - 1958-1961 (Box 1)
      - 1969-1973, 5 folders (Box 1)
      - 1979-1992, 14 folders (Box 1)
      - 1993-2005, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Development Committee
    - Correspondence and Minutes
      - 1990-1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1979-2000
      - 1979-1987 (Box 2)
      - 1988-1991 (Box 2)
      - 1994 (Box 2)
      - 1997-2000 (Box 2)
    - Notes (Box 2)
    - Port Oneida Meetings 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - Metro Detroit Council
    - Minutes 1942-1983
      - 1942-1959, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1960-1968, 9 folders (Box 3)
      - 1974-1979, 6 folders (Box 3)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Annual Reports
      - 1945-1965, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1969 (Box 3)
- Publications
  Publications (0.25 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically and contain brochures, pamphlets, programs, bicycling guides, and manuals.
  - Brochures and Programs (Box 3)
  - Bicycling Guides (Box 3)
  - Manuals
    - Hostel Operations 1961 (Box 3)
    - "Leaders of Youth Hostel Trips," 1949 (Box 3)
    - Leadership Training 1995 (Box 4)
    - Board Manual 2001 (Box 4)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files (0.5 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically by topic and include trip itineraries, hostel reports and proposals, histories, and materials related to Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore, including administrative files and feasibility studies.
  - Alaska Trip Itinerary 1968 (Box 4)
  - American Youth Hostel Report 1986 (Box 4)
  - Boy Scouts Merit Badge Project (Box 4)
  - Burfiend Farm House Proposal 1999 (Box 4)
  - Fort Custer (Box 4)
  - History of Metro Detroit Council 1936-1976 (Box 4)
  - Leaders Meeting
    - Policies and Notes 1987-2001 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Hostels (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 4)
  - Paddle Push Contest 1966 (Box 4)
  - Sleeping Bear Dunes
    - Administrative
      - Budget Materials (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Development (Box 4)
      - Land Drawings and Maps (Box 4)
    - Feasibility Study
      - 1998 (Box 4)
      - 2004 (Box 4)
      - 2005 (Box 4)
    - Port Oneida
      - Article and Program (Box 4)
    - Study 1998 (Box 4)
  - "Tips for Women Traveling Solo" (Box 4)
- Photographs
  Photographs (0.75 linear feet) are arranged by chronological order where available, otherwise alphabetically by topic. Photographs range from 1950-2004 and include topics such as American Youth Hostel construction and hostel sites and trips and events. The remaining photographs are undated and unspecified and consist mostly of trips and events.
  - AYC construction sites (Box 4)
  - AYC hostel sites (Box 4)
  - AYC trips (Box 4)
  - Burfiend Farm (Box 4)
  - Crested Butte Hostel, CO (Box 4)
  - Negatives (unidentified), 1 sheets (Box 4)
  - Paddle Push 1958 (Box 4)
  - Sleeping Bear Dunes (Box 4)
  - Sleeping Bear Dunes Activity Weekend 2001 (Box 4)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 4)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 4)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 4)
  - 1980-1989 (Box 4)
  - 1990-1999 (Box 4)
  - 2000-2004 (Box 4)
  - Undated, 9 folders (Box 4)
- Slides
  Slides (2 folders) contain unidentified images dating from 1968-1984 and images taken at Mott Lake in Genesee County.
  - 1968-1984 (Box 4)
  - Mott Lake (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks
  Scrapbooks (1.0 linear feet and 2 oversize folders) are all individually bound and arranged alphabetically by scrapbook title. Scrapbooks date from 1941-2000 and include photographs, newspaper clippings, and occasional ephemera.
  - General Events and News 1963-1969 (Box 5)
  - Erie Youth Hostel 1942-1960 (Box 5)
  - Foote Hostel 1956-1976 (Box 5)
  - Other AYC Hostels (China, New Zealand, Hawaii, Scotland, California) (Box 5)
  - Michigan Council Hostelling International Photos 1995-2000 (Box 5)
  - Publicity 1982-1984 (Box 5)
  - Stella Heavner Album of General Events and Trips 1944-1963 (Box 5)
  - Study of Michigan Youth Hostels by Thelma Bishop 1941 (Box 5)
  - American Youth Hostel Scrapbook, 1945-1981 (Volume 1)
  - American Youth Hostel Publicity Scrapbook, 1977-1982 (Volume 2)
Related Material
Three publications related to this record group are housed at the Bentley Historical Library. These include two newsletters Michigan Hostel News (call no. FR 2 A512 M624h) and The Happy Wanderer (call no. FR 2 A512 H252) and an activities calendar, Michigan AYH Beacon (call no. FR 2 A512 M624).